<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  
  <entry>
    <title>Create More, Consume Less</title>
    <link href="/blog/2021/create/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-01T00:44:13Z</updated>
    <id>/blog/2021/create/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Writing and learning are two seperate things but both are very powerful tools with which can help you to build your audience and opens up a new world of opportunities to you to discover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time we consume more and think that we are learning which is hoax. Whenever we stumble upon anything which we want to learn the first step is the absorb the material and then make notes about it. Think like you will be giving a lecture about the topic which you learnt. Making notes of your own will help you to deepen the understanding of the topic, a great example of this is feynman technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performing daily writing of what you learnt will create a reservoir of knowledge which you can then use for your success like sharing your learning with people online. This will also help you to improve your learning process because you will be getting feedback from the other people.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>YouTube-DL</title>
    <link href="/blog/2021/youtube-dl/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-02T00:44:13Z</updated>
    <id>/blog/2021/youtube-dl/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past few weeks, I am off from YouTube. My YouTube channel is getting mirrored on &lt;a href=&quot;https://odysee.com/&quot;&gt;Odysee&lt;/a&gt;. But I still follow my favorite content creators using Invidious, Odysee, and youtube-dl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As most of you would know, what happened with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2020/11/github-reinstates-youtube-dl-after-riaas-abuse-dmca&quot;&gt;repository of youtube-dl&lt;/a&gt; I am glad that it&#39;s back and functional again. Setting up youtube-dl for the first time can be troublesome for new users, but once you get the hang of it, you would not stop, especially with config, the download process becomes easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my config, and yes, I am on a Windows machine for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;-f mp4
-f 137+140/299+140
-o C:/Users/Joel/Downloads/YouTube/%(title)s-%(uploader)s.%(ext)s
--no-mtime
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refer &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ytdl-org/youtube-dl/blob/master/README.md#output-template&quot;&gt;Output Template&lt;/a&gt; for more details&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who wanted to get started with youtube-dl, here is a great video to begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My process of getting videos offline is simple. Get the link of the video from invidious and paste it into the command prompt. But if I am on my phone, I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe&quot;&gt;Newpipe&lt;/a&gt; to watch and download YouTube videos.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Trying Out Awesome WM</title>
    <link href="/blog/2021/awesome-wm/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-03T00:44:13Z</updated>
    <id>/blog/2021/awesome-wm/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I always wanted to get started with window managers, but the learning curve kept me away. So on 1st February 2021, I decided to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I didn&#39;t want to mess up the primary system, I went with the virtual machine route. For the distro, I went with &lt;a href=&quot;https://manjaro.org/download/#awesome&quot;&gt;Manjaro&#39;s community build of awesome&lt;/a&gt; after watching DistroTube&#39;s video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setup process was similar to that of any Manjaro installation. It took around 8-10 minutes to install, and after installation finished, the first problem I encountered was how to change the wallpaper. The easy solution was to install Nitrogen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s2.gifyu.com/images/2021-02-01-174146_2560x1080_scrot.png&quot; alt=&quot;manjaro after install&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, it took me more than 2 hours to configure the setup, according to my daily usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s2.gifyu.com/images/2021-02-01-174128_2560x1080_scrot.png&quot; alt=&quot;my setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of applications that I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URXVT (Terminal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ranger with W3M (Filemanager)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firefox (Web Browser)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rofi (Popup Window Switcher)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mousepad (GUI Text Editor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this video for more customization and setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am delighted with my current setup, nothing too fancy or too minimal. Get&#39;s the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Trying Out Spectrwm</title>
    <link href="/blog/2021/spectrwm/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-04T00:44:13Z</updated>
    <id>/blog/2021/spectrwm/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After my previous post about awesome wm, &lt;a href=&quot;https://fosstodon.org/@joeligj12&quot;&gt;Chrono&lt;/a&gt; suggested trying out Spectrwm. Spectrwm is a small, dynamic tiling and reparenting window manager for X11. It was for the very first time I heard about this window manager so I decided to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went with ArcoLinuxB since it has the spectrwm version available to download. The installation went fast since I didn&#39;t install any extra packages that ArcoLinux provides during installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now coming to Spectrwm, ArcoLinux has already configured most of the stuff so I didn&#39;t have to waste much time setting it up by myself. The keybindings are quite hard to find for a new user but since I knew where to lookup for the config I had no issues with that part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must say the window manager is quite minimal and easy to use if you remember properly the keybindings. ArcoLinux also comes with a few extra tricks at its sleeves. Such as preconfigured keybindings for most of the popular software, a key bind to change the wallpaper, and also a preconfigured polybar which is neat. It also has its own tweaks menu where you can set hblock, change the terminal theme, configure auto startup, and much more which is handy for a new user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall spectrwm can be the very first window manager for most of the new users and especially if you go with ArcoLinux since most of the stuff is already preconfigured and ready to use out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Gaming Laptop Are Becoming Boring</title>
    <link href="/blog/2021/gaming-laptop/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-05T00:44:13Z</updated>
    <id>/blog/2021/gaming-laptop/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For me, gaming is a medium to enjoy and not yell at friends like most of my friends do. I got myself a gaming laptop as a birthday gift. For the first few weeks, I played some of my favorite games and enjoyed every second of them. But I missed something that made me appreciate it even more and, that was playing it on low-end hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me get this point clear. All the systems which I owned till now were less than $300 in cost. Which also introduced me to the world of Linux since they were performing poorly on Windows. When I shifted to a $1000 laptop, I could feel the difference in performance, but that was all it for me. I could render my videos faster, play modern gaming titles &amp;amp; compile code quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when it came to gaming, I missed reading and watching tutorials online to get that last bit of FPS from the game on my older hardware. That was pure enjoyment for me since I could notice the difference it was making to the game after applying the tweaks. Some might not agree with me for the above point of view but, I feel that we have reached a stage where the law of diminishing returns makes more sense than before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I mean by that is we don&#39;t need expensive hardware to improve the workflow. Our experience will guide us to be better and more efficient at work by utilizing the systems which we own currently. For example, if I am rendering a video and it takes around 30 minutes to do so. I could spend that 30 minutes reading a chapter of the book that I picked up while my video is getting rendered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of 2021, I have stopped playing games and, I don&#39;t see myself playing them in the future. I have been focusing on my web development skills lately and, I could see the difference it has brought to me. I have more time at hand than before and, I could complete my daily tasks with ease.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reduction of Page Size</title>
    <link href="/blog/2021/page-size/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-06T00:44:13Z</updated>
    <id>/blog/2021/page-size/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days back, I came across the &lt;a href=&quot;https://512kb.club/&quot;&gt;512KB club&lt;/a&gt; that lists websites whose uncompressed page size is less than 512KB. I decided to give it a try. To my surprise, my page size was just under 400KB but, I wasn&#39;t thrilled with the result. So I decided to cut down even more so, I set out on this adventurous journey of reducing my page size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.postimg.cc/hjgSs1KQ/prev-min.png&quot; alt=&quot;Previous page size&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got rid of unwanted JavaScript code and CSS that helped me reduce the page size by 40-50 KB. I wasn&#39;t thrilled enough so, I got back again to debug what was causing the enormous page size. Luckily, I got my answer, and that was my favicon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A favicon is a small, iconic image that represents your website. My blog&#39;s favicon was taking around 300 KB, due to which every time I requested my blog, the favicon was adding its extra size to the final page size. Upon discovering this issue, I redid my favicon as 32x32 instead of the previous 256x256.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The indicated fix massively improved the page size. Now, my blog&#39;s uncompressed page size is 22.8 KB compared to the original 335.6 KB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.postimg.cc/3J7DYCKL/new-Result-min.png&quot; alt=&quot;Current page size&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the solution to our problem is right in front of us but, we don&#39;t attempt to look at it thereby, wasting time and energy on something different.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reading Computer Code Is Different</title>
    <link href="/blog/2021/reading-code/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-07T00:44:13Z</updated>
    <id>/blog/2021/reading-code/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learning a computer programming language is somewhat similar to that of learning a new language to speak. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.mit.edu/2020/brain-reading-computer-code-1215&quot;&gt;MIT neuroscientists&lt;/a&gt; reading computer code doesn&#39;t involve the region of the brain which is responsible for language processing. Instead, it activates distributed network called the &lt;strong&gt;multiple demand network&lt;/strong&gt;, which also gets activated during solving a mathematical problem or a crossword.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of computer code, the brain uses &lt;strong&gt;multiple areas&lt;/strong&gt; of multiple demand network. Multiple demand network gets activated only when there is a need to store more information and while performing mental tasks. The MIT team also found out that reading computer code appears to activate both the left and right sides of the multiple demand network. There is no finding of some region exclusively devoted to programming, but there is some possibility in those who have more coding experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Improve as a Writer</title>
    <link href="/blog/2021/writer/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-08T00:44:13Z</updated>
    <id>/blog/2021/writer/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The definition of writing can be different for many. For me, it&#39;s putting my ideas and thoughts on a sheet of paper. I spend most of my time in front of digital screens, that&#39;s why the sheet of paper interchanged with a blank document. Ever since I came across the 100 days of offload challenge, I wanted to test myself as a writer. I don&#39;t aim to be an author. It&#39;s just that I want to get better at expressing myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried blogging previously but, I failed at it, not because of a lack of ideas. I feared what people might think of my posts. In December 2020, I decided to reinstate my blogging journey with a fresh coat of new ideas. This very blog was born out of those unsuccessful ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since I started my 100 days challenge, I learned something new every day. I am noticing the difference in my writing style. I adapted forward my old notes from books and blog posts into my very own blog posts. So, don&#39;t think of yourself as someone who can&#39;t do anything in life. We all start somewhere with small and humble beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Create A Gemini Capsule</title>
    <link href="/blog/2021/gemini-capsule/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-09T00:44:13Z</updated>
    <id>/blog/2021/gemini-capsule/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past few days, the term Gemini has been trending on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gemini protocol is an application layer protocol for distributed hypertext information systems that provides access to simple, primarily textual documents in Gemini space. This is done with contemporary technologies such as TLS, thereby improving privacy and user agency relative to the Web. (Taken from Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very first question that arrived at me while exploring Gemini was how I set up a mirrored version of this very blog and, then I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://gemlog.blue/&quot;&gt;gemlog&lt;/a&gt;. It provides an easy way to keep a gemlog (journal) over the Gemini protocol. For creating an account you don&#39;t require any identifying information. Pick a username of your choice with a strong password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to access your newly created gemlog you need a &lt;a href=&quot;https://gemini.circumlunar.space/clients.html&quot;&gt;Gemini client&lt;/a&gt;. The one which I use is &lt;a href=&quot;https://gmi.skyjake.fi/lagrange/&quot;&gt;Lagrange&lt;/a&gt; a GUI client with cross-platform support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Gemini Capsule: gemini://gemlog.blue/users/kninja (All of my posts will be available over here)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>